<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd" [
<!ENTITY aqd_version SYSTEM "../version.txt">
]>
<refentry xml:id="aq_add_feature"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>aq_add_feature</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo class="version">&aqd_version;</refmiscinfo>
        <refmiscinfo class="manual">Aquilon Commands</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv>
        <refname>aq add feature</refname>
        <refpurpose>
	    Add a feature
        </refpurpose>
	<refclass>Aquilon</refclass>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
	    <command>aq add feature</command>
	    <group>
		<synopfragmentref linkend="global-options">Global options</synopfragmentref>
	    </group>
	    <arg choice="plain"><option>--feature <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="plain"><option>--type <replaceable>TYPE</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="opt"><option>--comments <replaceable>COMMENTS</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="opt"><option>--post_personality</option></arg>
	    <xi:include href="../common/global_options.xml"/>
	</cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>

    <refsect1>
        <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	    The <command>aq add feature</command> command creates a new feature.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Features are templates which get included from the host plenary template. There
	    are 3 kind of features: hardware, host and interface.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Hardware features are meant to perform hardware-related changes like turning off hyperthreading,
	    applying certain firmware settings or controlling power saving modes. When a hardware feature is
	    activated, the host plenary will include
	    <filename>features/hardware/<replaceable>NAME</replaceable>/config.tpl</filename>
	    just after the OS template. Therefore hardware features have access to the hardware description and
	    operating system information, but nothing else.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Host features are the most generic, and usually control software that gets installed on the host.
	    If a host template is active, then
	    <filename>features/<replaceable>NAME</replaceable>/config.tpl</filename>
	    will be included either before or after the personality template. If the <option>--post_personality</option>
	    option is specified, then the feature template will be included after the personality template; if
	    this option is missing, then the feature template will be included before the personality template.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The position where the feature template gets included depends on how the feature is implemented.
	    A feature template included before the personality template cannot take parameters, but the
	    personality template may override any settings made by the feature template. On the other hand,
	    if the feature template is included after the personality template, then it may take parameters
	    e.g. in the form of global variables set by the personality template, and the personality
	    template has no way to override the effects of the feature template.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The third kind of features are interface features. Contrary to hardware and host features which
	    apply to the host as a whole, interface features are meant to control the parameters of just a
	    single interface. When an interface feature is active, the
	    <filename>features/interface/<replaceable>NAME</replaceable>/config.tpl</filename>
	    template will be included once for every affected interface. The name of the interface to act on
	    is passed in the <varname>CURRENT_INTERFACE</varname> global variable.
	</para>
	<para>
	    To avoid template name collisions, the name of host features must not start with the
	    prefixes <filename>hardware/</filename> or <filename>interface/</filename>.
	</para>
	<para>
	    After adding a feature, the <command>aq bind feature</command> command should be used to bind
	    it to models/archetypes/personalities. A feature will be activated if the parameters of a given
	    host match one of the bindings.
	</para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
        <title>Options</title>
	<variablelist>
	    <title>Command-specific options</title>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--feature <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			The name of the feature. The name is allowed to contain slashes (/) to allow
			using subdirectories in the templates, but path components are not allowed to
			start with a dot.
		    </para>
		    <para>
			Feature names must be unique for any given type.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--type <replaceable>TYPE</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			The type of the feature. See above for the description of the possible
			values and their meaning.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--post_personality</option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Indicate that the feature template should be included after the personality
			template. This option may be specified for host features only.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--comments <replaceable>COMMENTS</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Feature comments.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<xi:include href="../common/global_options_desc.xml"/>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1>
	<title>See also</title>
	<para>
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>aq_bind_feature</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>aq_unbind_feature</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>aq_del_feature</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>aq_show_feature</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	</para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>

<!-- vim: set ai sw=4: -->
