<?xml version="1.0"?>
<refentry version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xml:id="add_network_environment"
	  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>add_network_environment</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo class="version"><?eval ${project.version}?></refmiscinfo>
        <refmiscinfo class="manual">Aquilon Commands</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv>
        <refname>add network environment</refname>
        <refpurpose>
	    Create a new network environment
        </refpurpose>
	<refclass>Aquilon</refclass>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
	    <command>aq add network environment</command>
	    <group>
		<synopfragmentref linkend="go-aq-add-network-env">Global options</synopfragmentref>
	    </group>
	    <arg choice="plain"><option>--network_environment <replaceable>NETENV</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="plain"><option>--dns_environment <replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="opt"><option>--building <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></option></arg>
	    <arg choice="opt"><option>--comments <replaceable>COMMENTS</replaceable></option></arg>
            <synopfragment xml:id="go-aq-add-network-env">
              <xi:include href="../common/global_options.xml"/>
            </synopfragment>
	</cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>

    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	    The <command>aq add network environment</command> command creates a new network
	    environment.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Network environments represent distinct administrative domains for the IPv4 Private
	    Address Space, as defined by RFC 1918. Inside the same network environment, the use
	    of RFC 1918 address ranges must be coherent and non-overlapping. A different network
	    environment however may re-use the same address ranges for a different purpose.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Let's consider IP address 192.168.0.1 is in use somewhere in the organization. Assume
	    you want to place a new server at an external hosting provider. This server has a public
	    IP address that is connected to the internet, but it also has a direct link to some
	    dedicated 3rd-party service. The provider of this service requires the use of the
	    IP address 192.168.0.1 to access the service. This presents a problem, since the same
	    IP address is now used by two different entities.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The problem can be solved by creating a new network environment for said 3rd-party
	    service provider, and registering the service address inside this environment. Therefore
	    the broker knows that although the IP address is the same, the two users of the address
	    are different, and the broker can select the right network parameters for both users.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Note that when there is an overlap between the addresses defined in two network
	    environments, then hosts in those environments may not be able to communicate with each
	    other directly. Setting up routing, NAT etc. to make such communication possible is out
	    of scope for the broker.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The default network environment is defined by the <literal>default_network_environment</literal>
	    key in the <literal>site</literal> section of the broker's configuration. All commands
	    will operate inside this environment unless explicitly directed otherwise.
	</para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection>
        <title>Options</title>
	<variablelist>
	    <title>Command-specific options</title>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--network_environment <replaceable>NETENV</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			The name of the network environment. The name must contain only alphanumeric characters, '_', '.' and '-'.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--dns_environment <replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			The name of the DNS environment that will be bound to this network
			environment. Any command that registers an address in
			<replaceable>NETENV</replaceable> and allows specifying an FQDN, will
			register that FQDN in <replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable>. If there is a real
			DNS server that serves the view <replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable>, then e.g.
			reverse address resolution will give you answers that are valid for
			<replaceable>NETENV</replaceable>, but not for any other network
			environment. If there is no real DNS server serving
			<replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable>, then it is still possible to populate
			<filename>/etc/hosts</filename> from the data stored in
			<replaceable>DNSENV</replaceable>.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--building <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Specify if the given network environment is bound to a single physical
			building. Currently this option is for informational purposes only.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	        <term>
		    <option>--comments <replaceable>COMMENTS</replaceable></option>
		</term>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Short description of the purpose of the network environment.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<xi:include href="../common/global_options_desc.xml"/>
    </refsection>

    <refsection>
	<title>See also</title>
	<para>
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>del_network_environment</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>update_network_environment</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>search_network_environment</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>show_network_environment</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>add_dns_environment</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	</para>
    </refsection>
</refentry>

<!-- vim: set ai sw=4: -->
